# 山东 青岛
Qingdao, Shandong
# 哈哈 到码头了
Haha, we arrived at the pier
# 快点啊
Hurry up
# 沙子口码头
Shazikou pier
# 一箱箱的鱼都是从船舱里搬上来的
Boxes of fish are brought up from the cabin
# 还带着冰块
Covered with ice cubes
# 这艘船上米鱼、带鱼、鲳鱼比较多
Mostly brown croaker, beltfish, and pomfret on this boat
# 都不是零卖的 要买需要买一筐是吗 对的
It’s not sold individually? You need to buy the whole basket? -Yeah
# 你分辨鱼是否新鲜就看鱼的眼睛
You can tell if the fish is fresh by looking at its eyes
# 鱼的眼睛发黄了 就不好了
The fish is not fresh if its eyes turn yellow
# 35斤 一共122元
35 jin(17.5 kg), 122 yuan total
# 没有8块钱给你找
I don’t have 8 yuan change for you
# 120元算了
How about 120 yuan?
# 好的 谢谢您
Fine, thank you
# 完了
Oh no
# 完了 想天真了  他们这边都是一筐筐的卖
I am naive. They all sell by basket only
# 不零卖的
Not for individual sale.
# 我刚才还得到一个消息
I just got a message
# 这艘船上来的都是鱼
This boat only contains fish
# 如果想吃梭子蟹 就得需要去别的码头了
If you want to eat portunus, you have to go to another pier
# 小港码头
Small port pier
# 看了一会 也没发现合适的
After looking for a while, I didn’t find any good portunus
# 看来还得去农贸市场买
We should buy it at the farmers' market
# 这个蟹 多少钱一斤
How much is this crab?
# 这个35元一斤
35 yuan per jin (70 yuan per kg)
# 这个大的90元一斤 是本地蟹
The big one is 90 per jin (about 180 yuan per kg). That is local crab.
# 本地蟹壳发绿
The shells of local crabs are greenish.
# 南方蟹发黑发黄
The shells of southern crab are black and yellow
# 您帮我挑一个比较好的吧
Can you help me choose a good crab?
# 最大的能有1斤是吧
The biggest crab is about 1 jin(kg), right?
# 怎么看蟹肥不肥啊
How to determine whether the crab is meaty or not?
# 你看这个位置 延伸到顶端了 比较丰满
Check this out. It extends to the top, so relatively plump
# 不肥的蟹 这个位置比较空
This part is empty if that's not a meaty crab
# 就拿这个比较肥的
I want the meaty one
# 一共60元   一共7两重
60 yuan total, about 7 liang (350g)
# 这个虾是体格不同 价格不同吗
Are different shrimps priced based on their sizes?
# 这种小的40元一斤
This small shrimps are 40 yuan per jin (80 yuan per kg)
# 这种大的150元一斤
The big shrimps are 150 yuan per jin (300 yuan per kg)
# 那这个太贵了
That’s too expensive
# 这一份90元2斤
This one is 90 yuan for 2 jin (about 90 yuan per kg)
# 您给我拿4个吧
Could I have 4 of these?
# 海捕虾45元一斤 4个虾16元
Wild-caught shrimps are 45 yuan per jin (90 yuan per kg), so 4 shrimps cost 16 yuan
# 生蚝5元一斤 20个13元
Oysters are 5 yuan per jin (10 yuan per kg), or 20 oysters for 13 yuan
# 扇贝5元一斤 10几个5元
Scallop is 5 yuan per jin(10 yuan per kg) or 5 yuan for around ten scallops
# 这个农贸市场是我见过最干净的了
This farmers' market is the cleanest I’ve even seen
# 地上几乎看不到菜叶 水渍
There are few vegetable leaves or water stains on the ground
# 除了干净以外 这边还有很多监控
There are also a lot of safety cameras on top of its cleanliness.
# 有海鲜交易纠纷 就可以查看录像
You can check out the surveillance footage if there is a transaction dispute
# 去前面走一下 看看有没有加工海鲜的地方
Let's move forward and see if there is a place to process our seafood
# 不管几个螃蟹都是一锅一蒸  一锅15元
To steam a pot of crabs, no matter how many, is 15 yuan.
# 这一大袋15元
15 yuan to cook this big bag of seafood
# 现在海鲜已经入锅了 等15分钟就可以吃了
Now the seafood is in the pot and being steamed. We can eat after 15 minutes
# 像扇贝 生蚝 它的肉直接从壳里掉出来了
Seafood like scallops and oysters have their meat fell out of the shell
# 先尝一个
Let’s try it
# 真的很鲜甜的感觉
It tastes fresh and sweet
# 不蘸姜醋汁也挺好吃的
Very delicious even without dipping the ginger and vinegar sauce
# 这个汁水多
Very juicy
# 在青岛有种豪气叫做把海鲜当饭吃
In Qingdao, people eat seafood as common as rice
# 这么一盘 原材料才18元
The raw ingredients of this whole plate of seafood only cost 18 yuan
# 现在螃蟹也上桌了  这个蟹是60块钱
Now the crab is also ready to eat. It’s 60 yuan
# 足足有7两重
About 7 liang(350g)
# 蒸熟的螃蟹红彤彤的 颜值很高
The steamed crab is red and beautiful
# 这蟹腿挺粗的
The legs of the crab pretty thick
# 先吃这个腿吧
Let's start from the crab leg
# 吃一口就是鲜甜的味道
Fresh and sweet taste
# 再来一个
One more
# 蟹肉很厚实
The crab meat is very thick